[Music]
Good evening everyone. Welcome to the
Lancaster City Council finance meeting.
and I am your host with the most
and we're going to get right into new
resolutions starting with
if you noticed my agenda's changed a
little bit. I gave you guys hints on
your resolutions and ordinances. So,
you're welcome. Actually, it was a hint
for me when I'm taking notes. Anyways,
temporary resolution 7925 coming through
public works, Miss Tiner.
>> And that will be Kurt. Are you
explaining that?
>> Good evening. So, this is a resolution
to allow us to apply for OPWC funding
for our 2027
paving program, which will include the
Hubert and Ree edition. Um, this is just
money that will supplement our 3M levy
money to go towards paving that
neighborhood.
>> No.
>> And that will probably be about what
>> 2027 construction. Yes.
>> Yes.
>> Yeah. Not not this coming year. We'll
have a resolution um soon
um to go for that project. This will be
the the following year.
>> Yeah. So the recent Huber area of the on
questions.
>> All right. Thank you.
>> Thanks, Miss Tina. I have Mr. Luenberg
as your second with three readings.
>> Yes.
>> Okay.
Temporary resolution 8025 also coming
through public works. Miss Tina.
>> Yes. This is for mowing for next year
for contracts. And unless Tim has
anything to say, it's the normal we do
every year.
>> He's shaking his head. Yes. Any
questions from anyone?
>> No.
>> And Mrs. Kit will be my second.
>> Okay. Thank you. Temporary resolution
8125.
Uh that is coming through finance. Um
that is for our yearly contract with
Reynoldsburg. If the law director would
like to speak on that.
>> Sure. Thank you. So, my office
prosecutes all adult misdemeanor crimes
that occur in Fairfield County and are
cited into the Fairfield County
Municipal Court. And that includes the
portions of Reynoldsburg that are in
Fairfield County. Um, and because of
that, Reynoldsburg pays us a a fee to
offset our cost of prosecution. All of
that money goes into the general fund.
It's approximately $10,000. Um, and
we're prosecuting between 60 and 70
cases a year for them generally. um we
try and keep our numbers on par with
what we're charging the county. Um the
county also pays us to do the
unincorporated areas and then
Pickerington um pays us to do what
happens inside the village or inside the
city of Pickerington as well. Um so this
is just the the annual piece to do
Reynoldsburg. Sometimes based on their
budgets um the municipalities or the the
political subdivisions will want to do
one year. Sometimes they'll want to do
two years. So Reynoldsburg wants to be
one year right now and that's where
we're at. We just need your permission
to negotiate a contract with them to do
that. Thanks.
>> Any questions from anyone?
>> Yes, Tom.
>> So, how do we come up with that number?
I'm just curious.
>> So, like I said, we basically know what
we spend per case on all of our cases.
Um whether it's prosecuting it for the
city, prosecuting it for the county,
prosecuting it for Pickerington or
Reynoldsburg. and we try and keep all of
those numbers about the same. Obviously,
we have a lot more cases from Lancaster.
Um, so Lancaster tends the spend is is
obviously more. Um, but the other three
we try to keep, you know, relatively
um what's the word I'm looking for to
they correlate essentially to the number
of cases that they're sending us to work
on.
>> So, you just keep a running average of
what comes out of Reynoldsburg. And
>> yeah, I have totals that I get from um
the clerk's office can give me totals at
any given point in time.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> Yep.
>> Any other questions?
>> Seeing none, I have three readings. Mr.
Als would be my second.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 8225 also through
finance. This piece um everyone received
an email from the clerk I think.
um law director sent us an email. So,
any questions on this? This is an
additional $37,000
allocation for mailing expenses in the
clerk of court's office,
which I found crazy, but they spend
$70,000 a year on mailing stuff, but
they also really don't have a choice.
Correct.
>> That's correct. I'm sorry. Didn't it
raise it when they had to hire somebody
to do extra work or that? Wasn't that
part of that
>> for the to?
>> Yes. When they when they added the
additional person, that person was
responsible for sending out notices to
all of the individuals who had failed to
appear or were delinquent on their
payment plans.
>> That wasn't really us doing it. We were
told to do that.
>> Correct. The state of Ohio required us
to do that. But also, so you know, um,
you know, kind of to Tom's point, we we
the clerk's office keeps track of all of
the cases and all of the case filings
and civil filings particularly are up
significantly this year. And our civil
filings are actually served on people
via first class US mail. So that's where
a lot of the expense is coming from.
>> Any questions?
No. All right. I have Mr. Als is my
second on that one as well.
>> Yes.
Thank you. And we'll go three readings
on both. Uh any other resolutions
we need to discuss. I didn't see any
previous. So ordinances
temporary ordinance 4925 that's coming
through the administrative services
committee. Mr. Luenberg.
>> Yes. I'd like to ask a uh safety service
director or the law director, whoever
wants to to address this one.
>> We can tag team if you'd like. Uh so
this piece is the annual pay ordinance
for the parks. Uh they got it in a
little bit earlier than the rest of the
city. So it's a little bit earlier than
all of the other paid ordinances that
you're going to be receiving later this
year, but essentially they're just
wanting to change some titles. It's the
same number of employees. They're not
adding additional employees. It's the
same number of employees. And this will
not be effective until uh January of
2026 or pay one of 2026, I guess I
should say.
But I'm open to any questions or if the
law director has anything else to add.
>> I just wanted to say procedurally,
Councilman Luckenberg and I talked about
um prior to the meeting, the probably
easiest way um I talked to the clerk
about this as well. Probably the easiest
way to do this is to go ahead and let it
be read three times and then table it.
And hopefully at that point we'll have
caught up with some of the pay
ordinances that should be coming out of
every other, you know, department or or
citywide pay ordinances. Thank you.
>> Thank you.
And uh Councilwoman Butler will be my
second. Yes. And we'll go three readings
and then we'll table it. So,
>> all right. Sounds good. Any other
questions on that one before we move on?
>> All right. Next is temporary ordinance
5025.
That is coming through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop.
>> Yes. Um this is just to kickstart the
tiff for the residential portion which
is the 90 to 100 units single family um
units along Sheridan Drive. So it
determines the overlay so we can notify
people and just get it started. Um we
are going to have to suspend. So just
one reading and Councilwoman Kes is my
second.
>> Okay. Anyone have any questions on this
piece? I do. Um,
we saw this come over our desk earlier
this year and at the time I raised a a
question about the width of the lots on
the plat that we were looking at and
they're only 40 feet wide.
And it's my understanding these homes
are going to be in the $250 to $300,000
range.
And if I was spending that kind of
money, I would expect a twocar garage.
However, our local zoning code won't
allow that because it says um
let me find the well
a two a 16 an 18 foot long uh wide
garage can only constitute a maximum of
42% of the frontage on the house. And
for us to be have to be able to have a
twocar garage in any of those houses,
the home would have to be 38 ft 4 in
wide, which would not fit on a 40 foot
wide lot with five foot setbacks on
either side. So I don't understand is
this a valid is this a plat that we are
agreeing to of 94 houses because that's
what they have shown consistently
and on 40 foot wide lots and if we're
expecting revenue from 94 homes in terms
of taxes
when the zoning code will only allow
maybe 60 homes in that subdivision.
Unless they're going for a variance,
which very well may be,
but then we're going to end up with a a
roadway of just all we're going to see
is 16 foot wide garage doors up and down
the road if everybody gets twocar
garages.
And I just I don't know that that's a
viable subdivision at 250 to 300,000
>> um
>> a crack.
>> Someone can answer. I It's I I
understand what you're asking. I don't I
don't know if it's relevant to this
piece that we're
>> Well, we're looking at a tiff and and an
incentive district
>> because you and I wouldn't buy a house
that look like that, but maybe someone
else is
there. Probably the the city has looked
at the kind of revenue that 94 houses,
the real estate taxes on 94 houses would
would uh bring in, but I don't see how
they're going to have 94 houses under
the current zoning code. I think that's
not it's not a a uh a valid depiction of
what's going to go in there. Unless
planning commission gives them a
variance. Um at which case, you know,
then I think we're looking at a just a
row of garages up and down either side
of the road if they do twocar garages in
a $300,000 home, which I would expect to
have in a $300,000 home. So, I'm just
asking the question. Is this a valid
plat that we can depend on?
>> This is not a plat.
>> Well, it's a it's a description. We've
seen it few months ago. We're now seeing
it twice in this legislation with 94
lots at 40 foot wide.
>> This is a design plan and design plans
are subject to change, right? And so,
this is what they anticipate doing and
that's what we would like to see them
do, but we don't know that this is
what's going to happen.
single family.
>> Who's we in this? And you're saying this
is what we would like them to see. I'm
asking my city council members if they
would like to see a subdivision full of
twocar garages up and down this the road
on either side because that's what we'll
get unless they get a variance.
>> You didn't let me finish.
>> I'm sorry. Go ahead.
>> We and I think I speak for the city
administration when I say we need single
family houses. We are desperate for
single family houses. We would like to
see some single family houses in
Lancaster one way or the other. And this
is the only project that we have moving
forward at this point. And that we is as
in the the whole city, the city of
Lancaster. This these are the new homes
that we have potentially and that's it.
And so I think the thought is let's get
the tiff in place. Let's make it, you
know, beneficial for the developer to
come here and build some houses. what
those houses look like is not ultimately
up to me or the administration, right?
Like you said, it's based on the zoning
code and then also the city engineer is
going to weigh in. Our planning and
zoning department is going to weigh in
and then if they need any variances or
ordinances, they go to either planning
commission or the board of zoning
appeals for that. Um, but that's further
down the line, way further down the line
than where we are right now. Right now,
all we're doing is is saying it looks
like there could be 94 homes and 94
homes could, you know, potentially bring
in this much money and that would cover
a portion of the the dollars that
they're going to have to put into the
ground to put the infrastructure there
in order to get a builder to come and
and actually build something.
>> Well, and that's that's my question.
We're assuming the revenue generated by
94 homes and I question what kind of
homes will be built there. If if there
are onecar garage homes for 250,000,
will they sell? I don't know. I don't
know if there's a market for that. I
listen, Lancaster, I know needs single
family homes. I'm well aware of that.
I'm just looking at this proposal and if
we're if we're anticipating revenue
based on 94 homes on a 40 foot wide lot,
I don't know. I don't know if that's
that's the the style of community that
we want to see in Lancaster. It's just
two-car garages up and down the street
with a 8 foot wide. I mean, a two-car
garage is normally about 22 A tight
twocar garage tight is 22 feet wide,
which leaves 8 foot of frontage on the
house to fit on a 40ft lot with a 5-ft
yard setback. 8 foot of frontage for the
front door and a side window. That's it.
And I can't imagine a subdivision like
that in Lancaster. I I would think if I
was a if I was a developer, I' I'd be
thinking more in terms of a 50- foot
wide lot that can give me a little bit
of frontage with a two-car garage. I
think those would sell like hotcakes.
And I I question whether a single family
or a single car garage will sell for
that kind of money. And maybe they're
not looking to build. I just heard 250
to 300,000 on the homes.
>> That's accurate. But can I remind you
that it doesn't matter really in terms
of what these properties bring in with
regard to property tax revenue to the
tiff. Um any money that they get in goes
towards that infrastructure and they're
happy with it. We're not offering or
agreeing or assuring them that they will
be able to pay off the money that
they're going to spend to put in that
infrastructure. So, if these houses end
up selling for, you know, $150,000 a
piece because people aren't happy with
the design and the look of them, the
developers just as happy to get that
tiff money back as reimbursement, you
know, as anything. They they're trying
to make something on the deal. And
obviously, we don't have the cash to put
in the ground for infrastructure
improvements. Um, and so this is kind of
the tradeoff. We have to we have to do
this in order to get the single family
houses.
>> Okay,
>> if that makes sense.
>> Kind of.
>> Hold on.
>> Um, this is going to in front of
planning. At least I've recommended that
they go back in front of planning
commission for the phase two. The first
phase was the multifamily units was
focused on that. They had a layout in
that preliminary plat that was kind of
grayed out. And oh by the way, uh they
had I don't know how many more lots than
they they did some grading and they
figured out that the terrain out there
wasn't going to allow them to get that
many lots. So they went fromund
I'm I'm guessing 120 lots down to 97
lots. Uh so this they're in the process
or at least I've recommended to them
that they update that preliminary plat
and take it to planning commission and
that's where we're at with the the
engineering of the project. The
multifamily
those plans are all in they're all being
reviewed. Uh the preliminary plat
the multif family looked great. That
layout looked great to me. I was just
concerned about the single family
portion of it. So, we'll see where it
goes.
>> Miss Biller,
>> um I need someone to educate me a little
bit, please. How were the de who
determined the dimensions of this
overlay
and how is how is that determined?
>> The tiff overlay is based on who owns
the property. Okay. And so, it's one
property owner for the entire parcel.
>> Thank you.
>> Yep.
Any other questions?
Seeing none, we're asking for suspension
tonight.
>> Yes.
>> I'm Mrs. Crates as your second.
>> Mhm.
>> Okay. All right. Moving on. Temporary
ordinance 5125 coming through finance.
Uh this is year. Did I write that
correctly? Yearly bond legislation for
the municipal court renovation. So I'll
let
>> year Yeah. yearly note bond. Yearly
debt.
>> Okay. So, so this is an annual piece
that we've been doing for quite some
time. It's the uh Colombian courthouse
cost overruns um that the county treasur
county treasur has graciously been
financing for us over the years. Um and
the courts have been paying down 180,000
on the principal payment plus interest
to the county for years. So, this is an
annual piece. Uh we're paying down
180,000 off of last year's note. So
they're renewing a note with the county
treasurer for 180. So this will be the
last time this one piece should come
before you because they'll be paying it
off next year.
>> Great time.
>> Any questions?
Seeing none. I have that as three
readings with Mrs. Bitler as my second
>> temporary ordinance 5225 that's coming
through public works. Miss Teener. Um
Kurt, do you want to come up and talk
about this
regarding the um easement for Fair
Avenue?
So this was a minor subdivision that
came in. It's the Ohio Power Company or
a
um expanding and building onto their
substation. It's at the end of East Fair
Avenue, east of Sheridan Drive, you
know, past uh James Road. It goes up to
the Medil School. Um it was a dead end
street. They wanted to do a new access
off of the end of that street. Our our
code doesn't allow that. So, planning
commission granted them a variance
uh to allow that lot split if they built
a culde-sac bulb at the end of the
street. So folks could turn around.
They've agreed to do that. They've
bonded the project. We're working
through the engineering. This is the
easement that they're giving us to allow
people to use that culde-sac bob to uh
turn around.
>> Thank you. Any questions?
>> No.
>> All right. I have that as two readings
with Mr.
>> Yes. Great.
>> Okay. And last ordinance introduced
tonight, uh, temporary ordinance 5325
coming through the law committee with
Miss Crates.
>> Yes. Thank you. Stephanie, would you
mind covering this for us?
>> Sure thing. So, at your special council
meeting on Monday the 15th, um, there
was a conversation about completely
banning fireworks, consumer fireworks
specifically in the city limits. Sorry.
And um so my assistant law director um
did a survey of kind of all of the local
uh political subdivisions that do that
and came up with a version of what we're
calling chapter 550
in part five the general offenses code
um that does that. And I'll just
highlight a couple of things for you.
Um, so in order to still have public ex
exhibitions of fireworks, um, we have to
have some process for regulating those.
Um, previously it was just simply a
permit. Um, but now that, you know,
we're completely banning consumer
fireworks. We have to make sure that any
public display, any any licensed
exhibitor is using the appropriate
fireworks um, and is actually licensed
to do that. Um and these are fire code
rules. A lot of them also the Ohio
Revised Code um governs and regulates
the occupation of being a licensed
exhibit exhibitor for purposes of
fireworks. Um and so that's why all of
that essentially is in there. Um, we did
carve out an exception for um
party poppers, smoke devices, snake or
glowworms, snappers, trick matches, and
wire sparklers, which are the smaller um
items that you can generally purchase in
like Kroger or something like that. um
those that aren't anticipated to cause
any largecale damage or public safety
issues, although they certainly cause
plenty of smallcale and you know
otherwise uh damage issues, but
regardless those are carved out and then
um there was one error that that
Councilwoman Kit caught in 5502C.
We had anticipated potentially putting
the permit fee into the the codified
ordinance, but then decided not to do
that because then anytime that you that
we wanted to change the potential fee,
we would have to come back before city
council and change that fee. Whereas the
service safety director has the
authority and the ability to change most
of our other fees. and we would want to
make sure that it's in line with all of
the work that police and fire are going
to have to do in order to um execute
essentially this this chapter of the
code. So, we didn't want to guess at a
number and just put a number in there.
Um we're going to let that be the
service safety director's determination
after they start doing this and start um
actually seeing how much work that's
going to require. Um, but so you're
aware, I know we had the question, this
doesn't allow just anybody to become a
public exhibitor. You have to go to the
state fire marshall. Um, it's a license
with a written exam, and then also a
proficiency basically, um, test to
demonstrate that you have the ability to
to, you know, buy these from the right
place, store these in the right place,
display them properly, um, etc. So, it
that's a that's a time-consuming and
expensive process. And also, you know,
there's a test. So hopefully um only
folks that should actually be doing that
are doing that. But regardless, if you
become a public exhibitor, um our our
fire police our fire chief and our
police of our chief of police, sorry,
getting all my chiefs missed mixed up.
Um they still have to verify that you're
complying with all those other rules
that the fire code requires. So the
distance from structures, the distance
from children, not doing it in the
public street, um not under the
influence of alcohol when they're doing
it, etc. So it's kind of a double layer
of protection essentially for for public
exhibits or public displays of
fireworks. Um and I think that's about
it unless anybody has any questions or
anything else they want to know about
it.
Anyone?
Okay.
Um, I have that as three readings from
Mr. Bisjack as your second.
>> Yes, sir.
>> Yes. Great. Any other ordinances that we
need to discuss?
Seeing none, uh, department updates.
Does anyone from the city have a
department update?
>> Yes, Miss Woody.
>> I'll have just a couple for you. Uh, so
first I just wanted to make everyone
aware. I think that we've talked about
this before, but as a friendly reminder,
you will have your first draft of the
2026 budget first reading on our October
6th board meeting. Uh, so I know
everyone's super excited about that. Uh,
second of all, I wanted to let you know
that we have partnered with the
Fairville County Health Department.
Bailey Blevens wrote a grant with the
healthy eating active living grant
through the Ohio Department of Health.
It is a safety grant. And so if you
drive up North Broad Street, right in
front of Mount Pleasant Elementary, they
have some temporary markings where they
are um just kind of practicing to make
that intersection a little bit safer for
pedestrians and the kids walking to and
from school. So if you see those, one,
they are temporary markings. Uh but two,
uh thanks to the Fairville County Health
Department for being willing to partner
with us to try and make that
intersection, that school zone safety a
little bit safer. um if it does go well
then we will look at making those
permanent markings. Um but they're going
to be practicing with it over the next
couple weeks and getting feedback from
the schools. So just wanted to make
everyone aware of that. And then lastly,
I wanted to say thank you to our water
pollution control department and our
storm water department. I see Curtis out
there. I don't think Stephen was able to
make it. But this year, United Ways
Community Care Day, uh Curtis and Jake
from Stormwater and Steven Welstead um
did a United Way Community Care Day
project where we had numerous city
employees that volunteered as well as
numerous other volunteers that were not
city employees. They all volunteered to
go out and clean up litter off of the
bike path and clean out debris and trash
out of our waterways specifically in the
Baldwin Euing and Feder's Run where we
had all of the flooding event earlier
this year. So, a huge thanks to them for
doing that. Uh I don't know, I didn't
see exactly how many pounds of trash we
pulled out, but I know it was
significant. So, just wanted to let
everyone know that.
>> Thank you very much. Anyone else?
Trish,
>> I just wanted to give council an update
that our uh city's bond council is
currently working on the lovely annual
Edy Road TIFF notes that will be coming
before you um for three readings. Um
sorry council clerk for reading that
have to read all of those aertin
um but yes so that'll be coming. It's an
annual piece out for the debt for the
developer note debt. So, and those won't
be paid off after that. Those are still
continuing for a while. Just to give you
guys a heads up.
>> Thank you. And and we like to go three
readings on those. So, she has to read
the big long
>> Yeah, I got you.
>> At least it's not theies.
>> That's That's true.
>> Okay. Uh any other department updates?
Seeing none, uh council meeting prep,
Mr. Porter. Thank you, Chairman
Skunover. Tonight, we do have one public
hearing. Um, it's regarding the zoning
map amendment due to the annexation of
163.4434
plus or minus acres from Greenfield
Township to the city of Lancaster.
>> Great. Anything else? Good.
>> That's it. Any other discussion items
for finance?
Seeing none, I will take a motion to
adjurnn.
>> So moved.
>> Second.
>> And we are adjourned at 6:28.
>> The regular meeting of Lancaster City
Council will commence at 6:40.
[Music]
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
Hi, this is Chuck Sims with the
Lancaster DARE program. DARE provides
students with skills to resist the
pressures of drugs, gangs, and violence,
and emphasizes self-esteem, good
decision-making, and communication
skills. This month, we're honored once
again to be chosen by Buckeye Family's
Buckeye Cares program. For sponsoring
our events, to donating DARE vehicles,
or supporting us financially, we say
thank you, Buckeye, for all of your
support.
[Music]
Please rise if you're able and join me
in a moment of prayer. God, grant us the
serenity to accept the things that we
cannot change, the courage to change the
things we can, and finally the wisdom to
know the difference. The September 22nd,
2025 Lancaster City Council meeting is
called to order. Please join me in the
pledge of allegiance.
>> I pledge allegiance to the flag of the
United States of America and to the
republic for which it stands, one nation
under God, indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als
>> here.
>> Mrs. Bler here.
>> Mr. Bisch here.
>> Mrs. Kra
>> here.
>> Mrs. Hoop here.
>> Mr. Luenberg
>> here.
>> Mr. Skunover
>> Mr. Sullie
>> here.
>> Miss Ter
>> And Mr. Wing
>> here. Let the record reflect that all 10
members of Lancaster City Council are
present. We now move to the reading and
disposing of the journal.
>> I have two of them this evening. One for
regular meeting minutes. dated September
8th, 2025 and another for special
meeting minutes dated September 15,
2025.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the journal.
>> Second.
>> A motion and second to receive and file
the journal. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign.
>> Reports of city officials.
>> I have seven this evening. I have email
dated September 9th, 2025 regarding
temporary resident or resolution 74-25
in Frederick Street sewer separation
project submitted by storm water manager
Steven Wilstead. Email dated September
10th, 2025 regarding 129th anniversary
copper cornerstone box removal and
discovery submitted by facilities
manager Eric Nolan. Email date is
September 11, 2025. Friends of the parks
invite submitted by council member Als.
Email dated September 12th, 2025
regarding resident pool survey submitted
by parks and recreation supervisor Steve
Gabville. Email data separate or
September 10th um through the 18th 2025
regarding regarding Northwater
Northwater plant costs submitted by pre
President Porter Denise Cruz and Auditor
Nettles.
Series of emails dated September 19th,
2025 regarding commuting community
development update submitted by city
planner Chasyn Carter. Email dated
September 22nd, 2025 regarding
intersection at 6 and High Street is
submitted by council member Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of city
officials.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the reports of city officials.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign.
Communications.
>> I have four of them. Email received
September 9th, 2025. Public records
requests on hazardous materials
incidents submitted by Taylor
Criten by Brown and Codwell. Email
received September 11th um 2025
regarding public records requests of
Telus Health as a vendor submitted by
Sarah Harmon of Smart Procure. Email
data September 19th, 2025 regarding
public records requests for Mr. Nisley
Lancaster City Council Facebook page
submitted by the Ohio Sunside request.
And uh Oh, that's it. Sorry, I thought
there was four.
>> Mr. President, like to make a motion to
receive and file the communications.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to receive
and file the communications. All those
in favor, please signify by saying I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign.
Special presentation and warrants.
>> There are none this evening.
>> Petitions and memorials.
>> There are no petitions or memorials this
evening.
>> Thank you. We've now reached the time in
our agenda for permission of voters and
taxpayers to address council. Uh there
is a threeminut rule to address council
and we ask that you do sign in at the
podium uh with your name and address um
as you be begin speaking. Please keep in
mind uh this is an opportunity to
address council. It is not a question
and answer session and you should not
direct any comments to any other
audience members. Thank you. Um and it
looks like we have somebody here
waiting. So
>> um my name is Amy Schlike. I live on Lan
Rico Boulevard and um more opportunities
to provide to council. So there are
things that um
>> Excuse me. Could you speak in
>> There are things that we are doing in
Lancaster. Um so coming up is um Charles
B. Shaw Gala. It'll be October 2nd
downtown in Provisions Bakery and Delhi
um fundraiser for I can't hear you. I
can't hear what you're saying.
>> We cannot hear what you're saying. You
need to speak up.
>> If you go to um Provisions on October
2nd, am I loud enough now?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. It is the Charles B. Shaw Gala.
And if you attend, it's the fundraiser
for the Harkham House because they need
the funds and you could buy some art,
but you could also enjoy just wine and
um lots of good food. Second, um we uh
we me so me and some other people have
started an exploration of possibilities.
It's going to be here in Lancaster at
the Crossroads Event Center. It is for
middle school age and up individuals
with disabilities
so that they can have a one-day free
event,
not a large time constraint for them to
try out art um in a fashion that they
can then maybe explore and revisit. And
you have a lot of art um and artists
around in downtown Lancaster. And so
it's something that we hope if they like
it then you start to receive the revenue
from it because they will visit all
those people downtown. Um lastly, this
is not really a question but sort of a
request. I have spoken with individuals
at the police department about sort of a
registry with 911 when and or if there
would be a household that would call. Um
let's say in my case, my youngest son
would call and he's non-verbal. I would
still want somebody to be sent, but they
wouldn't know that necessarily unless
they knew that information, which I
could voluntarily give them, much like
the State Highway Patrol will allow you
to give them information if you're
pulled over by them. Um, it just so
happens that Athens County has completed
and now has the peaceful encounter
program. It's a database. It's
voluntary. You sign up. It's meant to do
more than special needs. It's for those
individuals that might have mental
health issues or schizophrenia or
whatever. Um, but it's their voluntary
assertion to do that and sign up.
I think it is Clark Township, it's
Delaware. Um, they have begun with their
fire department basically a special
needs registry and that is not really a
database but a form. And so I don't
really care which way you go, if it's a
database or if it's a form, but I feel
like this is a lifesaving measure for
individuals, for first responders. If
they get in, if they address the issue
and they get out quickly, it helps
everybody. And I just want to make sure
that we're making the progress. And you
don't have to reinvent the wheel. just
go talk to Athens or um Clark count or
Clark Township in Delaware and you can
find that information out. And I'm
probably at time.
>> You've you've reached your three
minutes. Thank you for your comments.
>> Good evening everybody. My name is Rob
Nisley. I'm at 802 Pennsylvania Avenue.
Um I just wanted to talk to you guys
tonight about fireworks. Um, I am
opposed to banning fireworks. I believe
that it would be a shame for this
council to severely restrict or ban
fireworks in the city. Um, I believe
that the people have spoken through
their elected representatives at the
state house to legalize fireworks in a
very limited, in my view, capacity. Um,
I believe there are reasonable
restrictions already in state law on the
use and uh, proliferation of fireworks.
And uh I believe that the city should if
there's an issue with fireworks, I
believe there should be more resources
put to enforcing the law already on the
books as opposed to uh banning or
restricting them further. And uh
furthermore,
I would love to see um in regards to the
tragic events of last uh last week with
the assassination and martyr of Charlie
Kirk. I would love to see this city pass
a resolution honoring him and
potentially even some sort of a memorial
in the city erected to the free
discourse of ideas and uh the the
gospel- centered work of Charlie Kirk. I
think that'd be a very welcome addition
to the city. And with that, I will yield
back my time. Thank you, Mr. President.
>> Thank you for your comments.
Hi, my name is Daniel. And am I audible?
>> Yes.
>> Okay. My name is Daniel and I believe
this has probably been brought to
council's attention before because Ryan
and Amanda Everett are my neighbors and
I think that they're good at bringing
things to people's attention. But the
intersection of South High Street and
Chestnut Street is a pedestrian fatality
waiting to happen. It is not a question
of if, it is a question of when. That
intersection is on a block with a
church, a preschool, and a public park.
And horns and squealing tires are not
daily. They are hourly. I live right
there. I work from home many days. And
it is a miracle as far as I'm aware that
no one's died there yet. It is It needs
to be a four-way stop or a traffic light
or something of that nature. It it is
really I feel like I am gambling with
everything every time I drift through
there to go home. So I appreciate your
time and that's really all I had. Thank
you. Thank you for your comments.
>> Is there anyone else that wishes to
address Thank you, sir.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah. John Bradford, 1360 Frederick
Street, Lancaster, Ohio. Yeah, I want to
address fireworks as well. And I guess
one of the first things I'd say to my
friend up here who who I've not met
before, but uh yeah, I like the Charlie
Kirk idea. And also like the idea of
that Rudy Julie Giuliani had about how
do you manage crime in a city?
>> Sir and one of them is to
>> address your comments to council,
please.
>> One of them is to have a zero tolerance
for problems. And I'm going to say
fireworks is that type of problem within
our city. And um right now actually
there's no place pretty much in the city
of Lancaster where you could set a
firework off and be within the state
guidelines as a consumer.
And so we need some
stricter enforcement on that to stop
this type of abuse of fireworks within
the city of Lancaster. I've walked my
neighborhood several times. We have a
gentleman or a group of neighbors in
that neighborhood out there that just
thinks every year it's going to get a
little crazier, a little wilder, and
it's happening everywhere. So, that we
need we need some strict enforcement
here. And I think putting the word out
that that that type of uh we need to
restrict fireworks and uh I think that's
a good way to do it. So, I'm all in
favor of that. Thank you very much.
Thank you, sir, for your comments. Is
there anyone else this evening that
wishes to address Lancaster City
Council?
Seeing none, we thank you for coming
this evening. We'll now move on the into
the agenda with uh reports of standing
committees.
>> I have four of them. I have water water
pollution committee agenda dated
September 11, 2025 submitted submitted
by Mr. Wing. Public Works Committee
meeting agenda or minutes dated
September 18th, 2025 submitted by Mrs.
by Miss Tiner. Um, water water pollution
committee minutes dated September 19th,
2025 submitted by Mr. Wing and finance
committee meeting agenda dated September
22nd, 2025, submitted by Mr. Scoover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
to receive and file the reports of
standing committees.
>> Second. We have a motion and a second to
receive and file the reports of standing
committees. All those in favor, please
signify by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Reports
of special committees.
>> There are no reports this evening.
>> Thank you. We will now move on to the
time in our agenda for public hearing. A
public hearing regarding the zoning map
amendment due to the annexation of
163.4434
plus or minus acres from Greenfield
Township to the city of Lancaster.
Public hearings are conducted in the
following fashion. We will first take
public comment if there are any from the
proponents of the zoning map amendment.
After we received the comments of those
and uh those proponents, we would take
any comments from opponents of the
zoning map amendment and then we would
follow up with any rebuttal of only
those individuals who spoke as
proponents at the beginning of the
public hearing. So, um your comments
would be limited to three minutes and
moving forward. Do we have any
individuals here uh who are proponents
of the zoning proposed zoning map
amendment? Please come forward, state
your name, and make sure that you sign
in.
[Music]
Good evening, council members. My name
is uh Craig Monreef. I'm the attorney
for the applicant, Mark Powers, who owns
the the four properties involved with
this resoning. Uh just want to give some
background on this. This has been
working in lock step with both the city
and the county on both the annexation
and the resoning of these parcels. These
are parcels on both sides of 33. Uh on
the east side of 33, uh just directly
adjacent to my client's property is is
uh property owned by the port authority.
There has been uh uh extensive movement
on entering into a contract on that
property, both my client's property and
the port authorities for uh some
advanced manufacturing. And that is why
we are here before you to both annex
that property and resone it and the
property he owns across the street. Like
I said, I think this is uh an ideal
location for some type of advanced
manufacturing use with its highway
location uh and separated from the heart
of your residential district.
Opportunity for jobs to increase tax
base and just a location that makes
sense and I think a zoning that makes
sense. Uh planning commission has
recommended approval. Staff has
recommended approval. annexation is
before you and will be before you in two
weeks. Uh so I'm here happy to answer
any questions and uh thank you for your
time.
>> Thank you sir.
>> Are there any other individuals here
speaking as proponents for the uh zoning
map amendment?
Seeing and hearing none, we will now
move on to individuals who might be
opponents to the zoning map amendment.
Are there any individuals who wish to
speak in opposition?
Seeing none, we will conclude the public
hearing as there would be no opportunity
for rebuttal. Thank you for your
attention to this matter this evening.
We are now going to move on to the
reading of resolutions. Beginning with
the third reading of resolution,
temporary resolution 7325,
>> a resolution to amend permanent
resolution 95-22
authorizing the service safety director
to enter into a contract for
construction
of the northwater treatment plant
replacement project. This is through
water water pollution control committee.
Mr. Wing and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Uh thank you, Mr. President. I move that
council pass and gross and enter upon
the written record uh resolution
numbered 73-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary resolution 7325.
Any um comments?
>> Yeah, council member Wing.
>> Yeah, this just amends the authorization
for the uh North Water Plant because of
some final change orders.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the RO.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Spitler.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack.
>> Mrs. K.
>> Yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop.
>> Mr. Lenberg.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Scooter.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 7325 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary resolution 7425.
a resolution to authorize the mayor to
prepare and submit an application to
participate in the Ohio Environmental
Protection Agency Water Pollution
Control Loan Fund Program for the
planning, designed and/or construction
of the Frederick Street sewer separation
project to execute contracts and
agreements as required and to designate
a dedicated repayment source for the
loan. This is through water water
pollution control committee, Mr. Wing
and Miss Teener.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I move
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record uh resolution
temporarily numbered 74-25.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
pass gross and enter upon the written
record. Temporary resolution 7425. Any
discussion? Council member Wing.
>> Yes. This is giving approval for the
loan application for the Frederick
Street sewer separation project uh
taking place next year.
>> Any further discussion? Hearing none,
please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes. Mrs. Bitler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. K,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skuniver,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> And Mr. Wink,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution
7425 passes 10 to zero. Temporary
resolution 73 or 7525.
a resolution to increase receipts,
appropriate from the unencumbered
balance, and amend the certificate of
other sources and appropriations with
the county auditor and the special
improvement district fund 2020. Mr.
Finance Committee, Mr. Skoover and Mrs.
Ber.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and upon the
written record temporary resolution
7525.
>> Second.
We have a motion and a second pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary resolution 7525.
Any discussion? Council member Skunover.
>> Uh just as a reminder, we received a
small amount of additional funds that
need appropriated for the SID in order
to move forward with that.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Bller,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bjac,
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Lenberg,
>> yes. Mr. Skunover.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary resolution 7525 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary resolution 7625,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to enter into an
agreement for engineering services for
the Lawrence Street pump station
replacement project. This is through
water water pollution control committee.
Mr. Wing and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Uh, yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I
move that council pass engross and enter
upon the written record of temporary
resolution number 76-25.
>> Second.
>> You have a motion and second to pass
gross and enter upon the written record
sub temporary resolution 7625.
Uh discussion. Council member Wing.
>> Yes. This is authorizing the engineering
contract and paying for it from the 6029
fund.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion
hearing? None. Please call the role.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler, yes.
>> Mr. Bisch, yes.
>> Mrs. K. Yes.
>> Mrs. H. Yes. Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Skoover.
>> Mr. Sully.
>> Yes.
>> Miss Tiner.
>> And Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary resolution 7625 passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary resolution 7725.
>> A resolution to authorize the mayor to
prepare and submit an application to
participate in the Ohio Public Works
Commission State Capital Improvement
Program and to execute contracts as
required. This is through water water
pollution control committee. Mr. Wing
and Miss Tiner.
>> Council member Wing. Uh
>> yes. Thank you, Mr. President. Uh I move
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
resolution numbered 77-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record.
Temporary resolution 7725.
Council member Wing.
>> Uh yes. This is an annual state grant
that the city applies for every year and
if awarded um this will go towards the
Tiki Lane waterline replacement project.
Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call a role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lenberg,
>> Mr. Scoover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Wink,
>> Temporary resolution 7725 passes 10 to
zero. We have no resolutions for second
readings. Therefore, we will move to
first readings. Beginning with temporary
resolution 7925,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to apply for a grant
through the Ohio Public Works Commission
to fund the Reese Avenue and West Huber
Avenue rehabilitation project and to
declare an emergency. This is through
public works committee. Miss Tiner and
Mr. Lucknberg.
>> Council member Tiner.
>> First of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary resolution 7925.
Temporary resolution 8025,
>> a resolution to authorize the service
safety director to advertise for bids
and enter into contracts for mowing and
trimming of the city cemeteries. Again,
this is through public works committee.
Miss Tiner and Mrs. Kates,
>> Council Member Tiner,
>> first of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 8025.
Temporary resolution 8125,
>> a resolution to authorize the law
director to negotiate and enter into to
a contract with the city of Reynoldsburg
for their prosecution of adult
misdemeanor, traffic, and criminal
offense offenses committed in the city
of Reynoldsburg within Fairfol County,
Ohio, and to accept payment for the same
is through finance committee, Mr.
Skunover, and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Skunover,
>> what's the first of three readings,
please? First of three readings on
temporary resolution 8125.
Uh temporary resolution 8225.
>> A resolution to appropriate from the
unencumbered balance and amend the
certificate of appropriations with the
county auditor in the general fund.
This is through finance committee Mr.
Skunover and Mr. Als.
>> Council member Skunover.
>> First of three readings, please.
>> First of three readings on temporary
resolution 8225.
We'll now move on to the reading of
ordinances, beginning with the third
reading of temporary ordinance 4125,
>> an ordinance to amend title 3, chapter
915 and 916 by repealing and replacing
existing sections 915.04A,
915.05A,
and 916.08
C of the codified ordinances of the city
of Lancaster, Ohio, and to declare an
emergency. This is through water water
pollution committee, Mr. Wing and Mr.
Als.
>> Council member Wing.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. Um, I'd
like to make a motion that council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record temporary ordinance number 41-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion second to pass and
gross and enter upon the written record
temporary ordinance 4125.
Uh, any discussion, Council Member
Wayne?
>> Uh, yes. As you'll remember, this is the
W wastewater uh rate adjustment. uh
extends a 3% increase through 2029. And
the biggest change is um it requires
industrial users to pay the same amount
per gallon. Uh again, one gallon of
water is the same as one gallon of water
or waste water no matter who you are. So
this is important change and um a big
win for the residential user and uh I
urge passage.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes. Miss Spitler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kra,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes. Mr. Lockenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner,
>> Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 4125, passes 10 to
zero.
>> Temporary ordinance 4425.
An ordinance to amend Lancaster codified
ordinance part 7 business regulation
code chapter 709 cultivation processing
or dispensing of mar medical marijuana
or adult use cannabis by repealing and
replacing section 709.05
review and reappeal of adult use
cannabis moratorum. This is through law
committee Mrs. Kitz and Mrs. Biller.
>> Council member Kus.
>> Yes. Thank you Mr. President. Mr.
President, I would like to make a motion
that council pass engross and enter upon
the written record. Ordinance
temporarily numbered 44-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Temporary ordinance 4425.
Discussion. Uh, Council Member K.
>> Uh, yes. Briefly, um, we passed a
moratorum in 2024. This legislation will
extend that for up to two years. Um due
to legislation that's pending before the
state regarding the tax monies, uh we
wanted to wait before um council took
any action on it.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Essler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisch,
>> Mrs. Kates,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Ter,
>> Mr. Mr. Wing.
>> Yes.
>> Temporary ordinance 4425 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary ordinance 4525.
>> An ordinance to repeal and replace
existing permanent ordinance 21-24
section of the setting public
improvements inspection fees pursuant to
Lancaster codified um 1107.02A
and to declare an emergency law
committee. Miss Kates and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Council member Kates.
>> Yes. Thank you, Mr. President. I would
like to make a motion that council pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Ordinance temporarily numbered
45-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion a second to pass gross
and enter upon the written record.
Temporary ordinance 4525.
Discussion. Council member Kits.
>> Yes. Um the city wants to allocate fees
for inspections into a single into a
single fund and use a single inspector
instead of using multiple inspectors and
multiple accounts. Um and this will
streamline the process going forward.
Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Eels, yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler, yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kra, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luxenberg,
>> Mr. Skoonover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tinder,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Temporary ordinance 4525 passes 10 to
zero. We'll now move on to second
reading beginning with 4625.
>> An ordinance to accept the annexation of
163.4
434 plus or minus acres in Greenfield
Township and to declare an emergency.
This is through economic development
committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. CR.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> Yes. This is second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4625.
Temporary ordinance 4725.
>> An ordinance to amend the zoning map
subject to passage of the annexation of
163.434 434 plus or minus acres in
Greenville Township and to declare an
emergency. This is through economic
development committee. Mrs. Hoop and Mr.
Wing.
>> Council member Hoop.
>> This is second of three readings.
>> Second of three readings on temporary
ordinance 4725.
Temporary ordinance 4825.
An ordinance to authorize the mayor to
accept an easement for access to the
closed county infirmary cemetery on
parcel number 053318111
and to declare an emergency. This is
through public works committee. Miss
Tiner and Mrs. Kra.
>> Council member Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
the council suspend its rules and wave
the third reading of temporary ordinance
4825.
>> Second. We have a motion and second to
suspend the rules and wave the third
reading of temporary ordinance 4825.
Any discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Not at this time.
>> Okay. Thank you. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Bitler,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Kit, yes.
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sully,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
third reading of temporary ordinance
4825. passes 10 to zero. Council member
Tiner.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record temporary
ordinance 4825.
>> Second.
>> A motion a second to pass and gross and
enter upon the written record temporary
ordinance 4825. Any discussion? Council
member Tiner.
>> Yes. This is so we can accept a
permanent easement so that we can mow uh
continue to mow the um closed county
infirmity infirmities. I cannot say
that. See, now turning to you the
cemetery.
>> Uh, that's up on 37.
>> Thank you. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> Mr. Bishack, yes.
>> Mrs. Kit,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Luckenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Tiner, yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> yes.
>> Motion to pass uh temporary ordinance um
4825.
uh 10 to zero. Move to the first reading
of ordinances with temporary ordinance
4925.
>> An in ordin ordinance to establish
benefits, titles, and compensation for
parks and recreation personnel employed
by the city of Lancaster, Ohio for the
year 2026 and to declare an emergency.
This is through administrative services
committee, Mr. Lnerberg and Mrs. Biller.
>> Council member Lenberg.
>> First of three readings. First of three
readings on temporary ordinance 4925.
Temporary Ordinance 5025,
>> an an emergency ordinance delineating an
overlay in the relation to the proposed
Sheridan Drive incentive district within
the city of Lancaster, Ohio, adopting
the written economic development plan as
to the same, setting the time and place
of a public hearing authorizing and
ratifying the giving of notice to the
Lancaster City School District and the
board of county commissioners of
Fairfolk County, Ohio. All pursuant to
the Ohio Revised Code section 5709
um 40C
and is declared related rules and laws
and dispensing with the requirement that
is ordinance must be read on three
different days. Economic Development
Committee, Mrs. Hoop and Mrs. Craig.
>> Council member,
>> Mr. President, I would like to make a
motion that council suspend its rules
and wave the second and third readings
of temporary ordinance 50-25.
Second.
>> We have a motion in a second to suspend
the rules and wave the second and third
reading of temporary ordinance 5025. Any
discussion on the motion to suspend?
>> Um, we discussed it during finance. So,
thank you. It's
>> sufficient. Any further discussion?
Hearing none, please call the role.
>> Mr. Als,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Baylor,
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. Miss Hoop, I'm sorry. Mrs. Kit,
>> Mrs. Hoop,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Lockenberg,
>> Mr. Skunover,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Sullie,
>> Miss Tiner,
>> yes.
>> And Mr. Wing,
>> Motion to suspend the rules and wave the
second and third reading of temporary
ordinance 5025 passes 10 to zero.
Council member who?
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make a motion
that council pass and gross and enter
upon the written record. Temporary
ordinance 50-25.
>> Second.
>> We have a motion and a second to pass
and gross and enter upon the written
record. Temporary ordinance 5025.
Uh, Council Member Hoop.
>> Um, not this time.
>> No, no, no comment.
>> Uh, no. Any further discussion?
>> Hearing none, please call the RO.
>> Mr. Als, yes.
>> Mrs. Berler,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Bisjack,
>> Mrs. Kes,
>> yes.
>> Mrs. H.
>> Yes.
>> Mr. Luenberg,
>> yes.
>> Mr. Skover,
>> Mr. Sully,
>> yes.
>> Miss Ter,
>> Mr. W.
>> Yes.
Temporary ordinance 5025 passes 10 to
zero. Temporary ordinance 5125,
>> an ordinance providing for the issuance
and sale of notes in the maximum
principal amount of the $180,000
in the anticipation of the issuance of
bonds for the purpose of paying the cost
of the renovation of an existing
building for use by the city's municipal
court together with all necessary
impertinances thereto and declaring an
emergency. This through finance
committee, Mr. Skunover and Mrs. Filler.
>> Council member Spoonover
>> be the first of three readings, please.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 5125.
Temporary ordinance 5225,
>> an ordinance to authorize the mayor to
accept a perpetual easement for roadway
purposes on East Bear Avenue and to
declare an emergency. This is through
public works committee, Miss Tiner and
Mr. Lockenberg.
>> Council member Tiner,
>> it's first of two readings. First of two
readings on temporary ordinance 5225.
Temporary ordinance 5325.
>> An ordinance to amend Lancaster codified
ordinances part five general offenses
code and adopt chapter 550 fireworks.
This is through law committee. Mrs.
Kates and Mr. Bisjack.
>> Council member Kates.
>> First of three readings.
>> First of three readings on temporary
ordinance 5325.
We have all concluded the reading of
ordinances for this evening. Uh, we have
two pieces of table legislation. I don't
believe there's any indication that
those are coming off the table at this
time. Unfinished business. We have a
liquor license for Brew Yak LLC. Uh,
doing his Brussy's drive-thru. I saved
you from reading that, by the way.
>> Director.
>> Yes, sir. So, typically what we do is
wait until the chief of police has the
background information for the
individuals who are attempting to obtain
the permit. Unfortunately, that either
did not come from the division of liquor
control or it got lost in the shuffle.
Um, so what we had to do was some of our
own research. Um, the company that is
transferring the license to Brew Yak is
Thodo LLC. Um, they have had liquor
violations in the past. Um, so
personally, uh, based on my experience
with with what they did, they were
selling products that had THC in them.
Um, I'm happy to see them giving up
their license. They're giving it up to a
company called Brewyak. Um, from the
publicly available information about
Brewy Yak online. It is a a beer cave
type specialty situation. Um, and it is
a corporation that has um multiple
locations and hopefully a little more um
sophisticated business operation in
terms of complying with the law. Um, so
at this point, you know, neither the
chief of police nor myself could find
anything about Bruyak that would cause
us to give an objection. We'll just have
to, you know, keep an eye on on them,
monitor and make sure that that there
are no violations in the future and
then, you know, address that if there
are. Thanks.
>> Thank you.
So, do we take a motion to approve the
transfer?
>> Thank you. I'll now accept a motion to
approve the transfer of the license to
Brewyak LLC.
>> Motion.
>> We have a motion. Do we have a second?
>> Second. We have a motion and a second.
All those in favor, please signify by
saying I.
>> I.
>> Thank you. New business. We'll now move
on to committee updates or general
updates of council members. And we'll
begin with council member.
>> Finally. It's about time you start with
me again.
>> Thank you. Well, you're easy. You're
within the line of sight. So, there you
go. Um, I have a committee meeting on
October 30th and the only thing I could
think of was about two weeks ago DDL
hosted a seminar called Unlock the
Potential of Your Upper Floors. Um, it
was well attended by 12
business owners slashpropy owners. Um,
and there were speakers including
industrial specialists, um, people from
the city like the fire chief, planning
and zoning, building department. Um, I
thought it was very informative. Michael
Wing was with me as well. Um, and it
brought together all the resources for
the property owners to um, utilize or
move forward if they wanted to utilize
their third floor. So, I thought it was
good for downtown to utilize empty
spaces and bring in some more sources of
revenue. Thank you very much, Council
Member Wing.
>> Yes, thank you, Mr. President. Um, we
had our last water water pollution
committee meeting uh Monday of last
week, so I do have a few updates. Uh,
first, I want to give a very special
recognition to our uh operators in the
water department. I understand many of
them are working 12-hour days currently.
Uh, they have two plants they have to
keep running and a brand new plant still
slated for October 1st that they're also
getting up up and running. So, that's a
lot of work on their end. Um, water
pollution control has successfully
closed another combined sewer overflow
location, which is great news. And, um,
been seeing lots of comments, uh, here
and there on Facebook about the, uh,
Main Street sewer separation project.
Happy to report that phase three uh, is
is ongoing. That's the the portion of
Cherry Street that's closed. Phase three
is ongoing. Um, so far there have been
no issues and that is slated, that phase
of the project is slated to go through
October 10th.
>> Thank you, Council Member Bitler. Any
updates?
>> Nothing to report, sir. Thank you.
>> Thank you, Council Member Skunover.
>> Yeah, I'm going to piggy back on the
last comment Michael made the sewer
separation project on Main Street. I did
ask at the public works meeting, and I'm
happy to report that in that contract,
they are supposed to pave the whole
thing when they're done because
Right now, Main Street in front of
Circle K is like a I don't even know
what to call it, but it's really not
anything nice when I drive through
there. So, it's a mess. Yes.
>> And it feels that way. So,
>> kudos. Um, secondly, so finance, I
think, um, SSD Woody brought it up. So,
the budget stuff is coming. Um, and
I've mentioned it before, kind of stuck
it out there like your your department
head should be bringing budget
items or the year-to- date stuff to the
committee meetings. I know um
transportation and Mr. Deetsz did that
for us at public works. So, that was
nice to to see, but and I'm gonna go out
on a limb here, too. and the treasurer
and the auditor
are always available to help you dig
into your stuff. The budgets the budget
is a big deal and it's huge and I think
from committee standpoints we break it
up because we I mean it's a lot to
digest. So, I think when we're talking
about legislation from your committees
or anything like that, the one the
council members that aren't involved in
your committee, like I'm banking on you
to know what you're talking about. And
if you're saying, "Hey, we vetted this.
It looks good. You can trust me." I'm
not saying that that doesn't mean we
don't look, but you know, unless you
have an extra 100 hours a week to dive
into the budget, I remember the first
class that I went to that Mr. Stoen did
for new council members. I mean, how
many pages
did we go through?
>> 120.
>> Yeah. So, I'm not going to I'm not I I
don't have time to look at 120. So my
expectation is
you know what's going on so I can ask
you directly and save a little bit of
time. We did it before the meeting
asking about a piece from from the
parks. So, this is the time to
hopefully you'll you'll have time to
reach out to administration,
the auditor, the treasurer, and make
sure that you have your ducks in a row
to be able to point out something to the
rest of us like, hey, we need to have a
bigger conversation. So, that's that's
my update and that's what I'm hoping
that uh you guys will do. And if you
have any questions, obviously I'm
available as well.
>> Thank you. Thanks. Appreciate that,
>> Council Member Ter.
>> So getting closer to budget, I always
have about October or so or well August
or September have them bring their
tentative budget so we can start looking
at it now and ask questions about if
they're vehicles, hires, retirement
because that's important to know. So, we
went through that at our last meeting on
Friday. And the street paving for 2026
is now online. If everybody'd like to
look and then call and complain to your
council people because your street's not
getting done, that would be fun to do.
Um, so it's mostly W two and four this
year is getting repaved.
>> Thank you for your update. Council
member Kra.
>> Uh, no updates right now.
>> Thank you. Council member Als, no
updates. Council member Lockenberg.
>> I've got a committee meeting on the 15th
of October, 8 o'clock, uh, in city hall,
but other than that, no updates.
>> What room is it in?
>> Uh, 1980. Is that what
>> 1897?
>> 1897.
>> All right, there we go. All right,
Council Member Biz.
>> Uh, thank you, Mr. President. Safety
Committee is having their meeting
October 10th at 8 a.m. 1897 conference
room. Uh, one topic I know that will be
on the agenda will be discussing the
budget for the fire and police
departments. So, just making everybody
aware of that. Thank you, Mr.
>> Thank you, Council Member Single.
>> No updates at this time.
>> Thank you.
>> Um, yes, Mr. Mayor.
>> Yes, sure. Thank you.
>> So, uh, in response to the question
regarding the 911 calls in uh into uh
the police department. Um, I believe
they have the ability already to enter
notes when you call 911 based on your
address. The notes can indicate resident
is blind, lives alone, who their contact
might be. Um, disabilities of any type
can be entered there. Unless something's
changed since I retired in 2017, that
technology already exists and is already
available for use. I would also add that
our police officers are about 70%
trained in crisis intervention uh
training uh to deal with people in
crisis whether it be disability and or
mental health crisis or addiction or
whatever crisis they might be uh facing.
I think it's a a huge benefit for us
over other communities because most
cities are lucky to have 10 to 15% of
their officers trained in crisis
intervention training. But uh I'll
double check with the police department.
I'm pretty sure that technology is
already available to address uh specific
nodes for a specific address regarding
any issue that resident might have.
Chestnut and High,
we will be coming forward with a plan to
improve that intersection sometime uh in
the not too distant future, but I am not
aware of any pedestrian crashes up
there. Uh not in recent memory. Anyway,
it doesn't mean that everything that our
uh speaker uh said is not accurate. Um,
I have near crashes there when I drive
through there on time and you can't put
a number to those. They didn't happen.
So, there's no stat checking a block
saying that you have 15 near crashes in
a week or whatever it might be. So, it
is an area of concern and we do have uh
a plan to address that intersection. And
then the last thing I would say, we
talked about legislation for municipal
court uh money for additional uh
postage.
uh that is directly related as mentioned
to the hiring of an additional staff
member to mail notices required by the
Ohio Revised Code in a change that took
place in the mid year. If you recall
when the clerk came in, she asked for
two employees and I actually persuaded
her to ask for one and see how it worked
out. I'm happy to report that one has
worked very well for her and she has no
plan on coming back and asking for a
second employee. um at least at this
time she's very comfortable with where
they're at. It the job is being done and
being done well. So uh that worked out
pretty well for us. So thank you, Mr.
President.
>> Thank you, Mr. Mayor. We'll now move on
to the announcement of scheduled
meeting.
>> Oh, excuse me.
>> I just had one other council member
Craig.
>> I just wanted to take this opportunity
to congratulate our mayor on his
induction to the Veterans Hall of Fame
for this year. Congrats. Very well
deserved.
>> Congratulations.
[Applause]
Thank you.
>> Announcement of scheduled meetings.
>> Okay. Next regular sessions of council
October 6, 2025 at 6:30 p.m. in council
chambers and then October 20th, 2025 at
6:30 in council chambers.
>> Special scheduled meetings.
>> I have none.
>> Regularly scheduled committee meetings.
I have um finance committee October 6th
at 6 pm. Council chambers safety
committee uh October 10th at 8 a.m. City
Hall 1897 conference room administrative
committee October 15th at 8 a.m. Bless
you. Um city hall 1897 conference room
and then economic development committee
October 30th at 7:30 a.m. and the city
hall 1897 conference room.
>> Thank you. Reading of bills. I have one
for MNCO for publications of ordinances
$111.82.
>> Mr. President, I like to make a motion
we pay the bill.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to pay the
bill. All those in favor, please signify
by saying I.
>> I.
>> I. All those opposed, same sign. Thank
you. There's no need for an executive
session. I will now entertain a motion
to adjurnn.
>> Mr. President, I'd like to make that
motion we adjourn.
>> Second.
>> Have a motion and second to adjurnn. All
those in favor, please signify by saying
I. I.
>> All those opposed, same sign. We are
adjourned. Please remember to sign your
legislation before you leave this
evening. Uh please try to stay dry. I
think everybody's heard the rain.
[Music]
The Frankie Smith Funeral Home and
Crematory in Lancaster and the Johnson
Smith Funeral Home in Baltimore have a
long and wonderful history of serving
our community. Feel free to give us a
call at 74-653652.
Stop in and see us at either of our two
locations, 405 North Columbus Street in
Lancaster and 207 South Main Street in
Baltimore. Respect for tradition, regard
for change.
>> Hi, this is Chuck Sims with the
Lancaster DARE program. DARE provides
students with skills to resist the
pressures of drugs, gangs, and violence,
and emphasizes self-esteem, good
decision-making, and communication
skills. This month, we're honored once
again to be chosen by Buckeye Family's
Buckeye Cares program. For sponsoring
our events, to donating DARE vehicles,
or supporting us financially, we say
thank you, Buckeye, for all of your
support.